Hello and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan, and today we're gonna
be doing a lecture on hybridization,
and I say the word mini up there,
but that's probably a little bit
misleading because this video is gonna
be a longer one because we're gonna
be going through all of the theory and
the practice of using hybridization.
If you're interested in going straight
to the practice problems asked, forward
through the video, I put in chapter
markers on the YouTube video so you can
go directly to it so that way you can be
able to study directly the things that
you need to know for how to do an exam.
However, you know, the best way
to be able to understand anything
to get tackle any problem is by
understanding the theory behind it.
So if you're someone that's just trying
to cram, I would recommend you actually
listen to all the little details.
Um, so where's it really starting?
So we're going to just understand
the basics of covalent bonding.
So it starts all with balance bond
theory, which is we look at the balanced
electrons and we're specifically looking
at the outermost layer of those electrons.
And how they're all situated in the
individual atomic orbitals of the atoms.
Now, when the little atoms get
close together, their orbitals will
overlap slightly and they can share
electrons, especially whenever
you have a half filled orbital.
But it can create a pair between both
of them, and we can share an electron.
And that sounds all great, right?
That's how we learned it in high
school chem, and that's how we've
described it, you know, since even
chem three A or all the basics.
So how's that work?
So let's say if I have
like a hydrogen atom.
It has a one S one electron,
so a single electron.
So the way that you generally
would draw it right, is you would
draw that S orbital, it would
have one little electron in it.
You draw another S orbital, it
also has one little electron,
and we would overlap them, right?
So as they overlap, it's gonna
make a pair between those two.
So we can make a pair between
an S orbital and an S orbital.
Great.
And there's a lot of overlap there,
so it's a really strong bond.
What else could you have?
Well, when we're looking at this, we're
thinking of, all right, what's the last
lonely electron in the valence level?
So, you know, back to hydrogen.
All right, it's one S one.
All right.
So then if you think
of, all right, fluorine.
Well, okay, what are its valence?
Well, it has two s, two two P five.
So it has one electron in the P
level that does not have a partner.
So, alright, if we want
to have another overlap.
You can have the S orbital and then
you can draw AP orbital, right.
Interacting with each other.
So you got s and p and they
can interact and make a really
strong bond because there's a lot
of overlap on the end of that.
Right.
So we have a little dot on both
orbitals and they're both being
shared and we can make a bond.
Right.
Same thing if I have my two fluorines.
Well, all right.
Well, we just talked
about the orbital, right?
The last orbital for,
that's another P orbital.
So if we have it where, let's say we
draw a P orbital from one fluorine and
then we wanna do the P orbital from
another fluorine, well they can overlap
with one another and we can have a
P to P type of interaction, right?
So it's all about those orbitals
fitting together really, really well,
making a very strong interaction.
And that's what we're gonna
be diving into is because.
The more you think about it,
there's a lot of little things that
probably never really made a lot
of sense and your teacher probably
glazed over it a little bit.
Let's kind of dive in a little bit more.
Specifically.
When a covalent bond is formed is
when two orbitals are overlapping.
Now you gotta, in order for this
to work, right, the following
cases need to be in play.
The orbital of one atom has to
overlap with the orbital the second.
The next thing that was always at
play is that each one has to have
a single electron from each one in
order for them to both be shared.
Now, it's not only electrons
that we have this pair, right?
You have to remember that the entire
thing is that there's an attraction
between the electron and the
positively charged nuclei, right?
And that's where that, that
overall interaction's gonna happen.
So the more over overlap we
have, the stronger the bonds.
So the ones I mentioned above.
Are the ones we're looking for, right?
S to S, P. P to P, right?
It has to be one of those.
They have to have a lot of overlap,
and if they don't, well, it's not
gonna be that strong of a bond.
So whenever we have this strong
bond of SSPP or sp, this is what
we call a Sigma bond, right?
This is the beginning
of a single bond, right?
How to interact and overlap that.
So, okay, so how would this
whole entire thing work?
So let's say if I had a carbon
bonding to end of the carbon.
Well, if we were to look at it in
the traditional sense of balanced
bond theory, we would first fill in
our valance electrons and we see,
okay, we have these two electrons
that are all alone for carbon.
So, okay, it can make two bonds,
and you're like, wait a minute.
I thought carbon makes four bonds.
I thought that was one
of our bonding trends.
And you're right.
So there's some problems with
this theory already, right?
We have to be able to fill in the,
fill in the entire things, okay?
But let's just play along, see
what kind of bonds we can make.
All right.
So we have these two
little electrons up here.
They can make two bonds.
So what kind of bonds can they have?
So the first one is all
about that sigma bond.
So, okay, we're gonna
draw our P orbital, right?
It has those double lobes and
we're gonna overlap them, right?
So just like so.
All right.
This is what we call a Sigma bond.
There is overlap with these right now.
The next one that's possible is, let's
say if this wants to bond a little bit
more, is you can create a high bond.
So, okay, we just drew
the PX orbital, right?
So it's going along our xxi.
So we can also draw like a PY
orbital or even a PZ orbital, you
know, going on our Cartesian axis.
To show all the different possibilities of
parallel, but right now our atomic orbital
only shows that we actually have two.
So, all right, we're
gonna go along with it.
Okay.
We see that these two red ones, they're
both parallel with one another, and
what's gonna happen is that these
orbits are going to overlap with
each other and make a very diffuse
orbital be between behind them.
All right, so this is our pyon.
Now, when I say diffuse, this matters
because this refers to the strength.
You see those sigmas right here,
right at the middle, um, are
overlapping completely, right?
You see that?
So they're really close together,
whereas the pies, they kind of
gotta stretch in order to be able to
kind of reach in that general area.
So Sigma is stronger than pie and
it's gonna lead to a stronger overlap.
So that's some things that keep
in mind as we move forward.
So, okay, let's try to see if we can
dive into why we're, we can't make
four bonds or go farther in this.
Okay, so clearly we're missing something.
Let's look at another example and see if
we can really spot where the problem is.
So, okay.
One of the things is water, right?
One of the, the molecules of life, one of
the ones we have to understand completely.
If you were to study water, right, and
you were to actually look at the bond
angles with water, one of the things
about it is that what you would find
is it's roughly around 104.5 degrees.
Great.
You know, that's what Vesper theory says.
That's what actual data says.
Let's see if it makes sense based
on what we know of orbitals.
Okay, so if we look at the valence
levels, right, so we look at two s, and
then we look at two P. We know that it
has six valence electrons, so we got 1,
2, 3, 4, 5, 6, so we can make two bonds.
Fantastic.
That's exactly what we want.
So we're gonna be combining
with those two hydrogens.
So all right, we'll put
'em in our two of our AEs.
So we're gonna make one
orbital that's on the Y axis.
We're gonna do another orbital that's
on the x axis, and that's gonna be
bonding to each of our little hydrogens.
Okay?
Alright.
We're gonna put one hydrogen on one
axis that's gonna bond to its S orbital.
Then we'll put another
hydrogen on the Y axis.
Great.
So we put all that there.
So we have this PP to S interaction.
That's exactly what we want, but.
Wait a minute.
If I'm looking at X and Y Cartesian
axis, what's the bond angle that's here?
This is 90 degrees.
That doesn't explain what data shows.
So it's not matching at all.
That's a problem.
So we need something more, right?
We need to know about how
the entire picture, right?
So bounce bond theory
needs something extra.
This is where quantum
mechanics comes in, right?
And all of our eyes glaze
over like, oh God, not again.
So one of the big equations
from that was this guy.
It's the Schroer equation,
which HCI is equal to eci.
Now, the SI function, this is the
most important part, is because
this is known as the wave function,
which gives you details on where
the electron is most probably
located right around its orbitals.
So it gives you information
about the orbitals.
Now it works really
well for isolated atoms.
However, when two atoms get a little
closer together, well, they interact
with each other and they change
the way it functions as a result,
because you have two different
things interacting with each other.
Same thing as you were to talk to somebody
and have an interaction with them, right?
Your feelings towards them and how
you think about them is going to
change, meaning that every time you
see them, maybe you'll get excited.
Maybe it'll be like, oh God, not again.
You're gonna have a reaction.
So the wave function changes as it comes
into contact because it needs the bond
and it wants to try to space everything
out to be in the perfect spot, right?
So low energy, low anxiety, it's,
it wants to include everybody.
So what's gonna happen is that
Wave Wong function's gonna change.
It's going to lead.
That atomic orbital is gonna make a
new shape, a new hybridized shape.
Now what's gonna happen is all the
orbitals that are taking apart in bonding.
Are gonna kind of add
on top of each other.
It's gonna make a combination
of all of them together.
So this is what we call a linear
combination of atomic orbitals.
Now depending on your course
level, you might need to know
the exact details of this.
Usually it's not until your junior
year when you're taking physical
chemistries when you need that.
But for gen chem, all we need to know
is that this is called hybridization.
Meaning that those atomic orbitals
are gonna change their shape
to fit the vesper geometries.
They're gonna orient themselves, so
that way it pushes everything to be
equal distant, changing into this new
shape to be able to talk about bonding.
All right, so how does this
entire thing kind of work in
terms of hybrid orbitals, right?
How does that really change?
Okay, so our head's right,
spinning a little bit.
So we have these new orbitals
that we're talking about.
So first thing, right,
is talking about oxygen.
Okay?
So oxygen had those six pounds, electrons.
So that's what we're talking about when
we talk about a isolated atom, right?
It's not interacting with anything,
it's just by itself, nothing changed.
However, we need to be able to
calculate hybrid orbitals, right?
So it's pretty easy to do.
The big thing is, is that these
hybrid ALS have a set set labeling
and it's equivalent to your electron
groups from Vesper or your steric
number, whatever you might call it.
So what happens here is, well,
okay, so in water, what did
we see in the Lewis structure?
Okay, so water bonds to two oxygen,
or sorry, two hydrogens, right?
So our oxygen bonds to two hydrogens
and we have two lone pairs.
Okay?
So two lone pairs, two hydrogens.
That's a total of four groups, right?
So if we have four groups, we need
four hybrid orbitals to connect
to those four groups, okay?
It's gonna be the entire idea.
And if you're like, I don't remember what
water looks like, you know, here you go.
Right?
You see those four individual
groups, um, and they, you know,
that revolve around your geometry.
Okay?
So we have our original shape, right?
So when it comes to our
isolated atom, nothing changed.
But being that we need four groups,
what is gonna happen is we need
to change those four orbits where
they're gonna be essentially.
Relaxing down.
So the P orbitals are gonna relax down.
The S orbital is gonna
get a little bit excited.
It's gonna be kind of like an
average in between of the energy.
So four atomic orbitals go in,
four hybrid orbitals come out.
So the way that works is S is going in
and we have the three P orbitals, right?
So being that we had the ones
from two P on the left here,
we have all three of these.
So we have all this little character
being added together, A little
bit of S and the three Ps. Okay.
What can we call this guy?
Well, let's be original, right?
Let's call it SP to the third power
being that, hey, SP three being that
we're combining a little bit of each.
So how do we fill in
the electrons from this?
Well, we're gonna do the same thing we
always done with electron configuration.
We had six electrons we're gonna
fill across because they're
degenerate with one another.
All the same energy.
And what does it tell you is, Ooh, this
gives you some interesting information.
It shows you, Hey, you have room for
two bonds, and you can show the two
loan pairs, and they're all equivalent
to each other when it comes to their
energy, and that's what that's showing.
When you look at that Lewis
structure above, it helps
explain the entire picture.
Whereas before, it's like you
had a random lo random loan pair
on a lower energy level, one on
a higher, there's these bonds.
It's like this kind of weird,
like I'm just listening to my
instructor and just filling it in.
What does this kind of tell you
is that okay, one is that it tells
you that you have this 25% of its s
character, 75% of its peak character.
It's lowering the energy of these
orbitals and it's given you this
brand new shape, which is gonna
lead to the tetrahedral geometry.
Or all these different vesper shapes.
Let's dive in a little more.
All right, so when does this work?
Does it work?
All the time.
All right, so for this
to hold true, right?
This has to be able to predict
chemical and biological behavior.
That's the most important thing, right?
If it doesn't predict
behavior for chemicals.
It's a useless theory, right?
It has to be able to predict it.
And this is something that helped be
able to, to shape how we understand
the structures of major proteins,
DNA, all these kinds of molecules.
It's what really led it to it when it was
first discovered in around the 1930s, or
understood when Linus pawing first started
to come up with a, you know, come up with
this theory to describe these things.
So the whole idea here is that hybrid
orbitals do not exist on isolated atoms.
They have to form a bond.
Okay, so now is this every bound Adam?
And the sad thing is no, it
has to form at least two or
more bonds for this to happen.
So if you see something where once
you have that historic number is equal
to at least two, then it can occur.
Same thing applies to anything that
makes a double or a triple bond as well.
They will also hybridize because it's
all about trying to place the electrons
in the most relaxed possible way.
So now what about the
shapes and the orientations?
Well, they're similar to SP DNF, but
it's a combination of SP DNF, meaning
it's gonna make a whole brand new shape.
So essentially is that whenever
you have these atomic orbitals
going in, you're gonna have a set
of hybrid orbitals that are gonna
be generated as a result of that.
So what does that kind of telling you?
Normal words.
So let's say if I ster numbers equal to
three, so I'm bombing to three groups.
That means I need three atomic
orbitals to make that happen.
However, it needs to lower its energy, so
it's gonna create three hybrid orbitals.
So three, three, and three
all across the board.
Same thing.
If I had a static number
of, let's say five, right?
So I need, I have five groups I
need to attach to, so I'm gonna use
five atomic orbitals, you know, that
are, they're, they're gonna start
interacting with things and they're
gonna convert into five hybrid orbitals.
They're gonna change, is
gonna be the whole idea there.
Now when we create these hybrid orbitals,
they're all the same energy, right?
So it's somewhere in between
your original Atomics.
So if you have like two Atomics
that are like here, you know,
your hybrid's gonna be like right
in the middle of those, right?
It's the whole idea.
So then they're gonna be the exact
same shape and the exact same
energy, um, which is gonna be good.
And they all add together right?
Now.
The other thing is too, like if
you're, you know, you don't have to
be an expert at all these things.
Above is because they're gonna,
essentially, they're gonna make
the shape of your geometries.
So if you have a Vesper chart or
you're memorizing and starting to
learn it, it's gonna match that.
So it's not, you know,
not the worst thing ever.
It's gonna be the exact same thing.
Now what else is there?
Well, in terms of how do you
kind of fit all these things?
What goes in hybrid or
builds, what doesn't?
'cause that's probably the hardest part.
So when it comes to a sigma bond,
right, that's a hybrid orbital.
Same thing with lone pairs.
So they both go in hybridized orbitals
because that's what determines.
How many electronic groups you have
right around all the central atoms.
That's like the base layer.
Now the double bonds, whenever you
have a double or triple, this is when
we'll use our un hybridized orbitals,
meaning your original orbitals.
So, uh, usually it's P
or maybe the D orbitals.
I'm gonna do that now for whenever you
have single double and triple bonds.
It's a combination of all
these working together.
'cause remember, every
orbital holds two electrons.
So if you wanna do a single,
it's just gonna be Sigma.
If you wanna do a double, well, you need
four electrons, meaning two orbitals.
So Sigma's gonna come in and a pi
orbital, if you want a triple, it's
gonna be sigma and two pi orbitals.
So it's be three orbitals
altogether working together.
And that's gonna be kind
of the whole idea, right?
And that's one of the things I'd
highly recommend you write down.
So that's gonna help you be able to
figure out all those little details.
Let's go on to our how to guide, right?
And that's probably where if you're like
trying to figure out like where to kinda
watch and you just wanna watch a shorter
video, if you were fast forwarding around
this, this is where most likely I'm
gonna be doing that with the editing.
Alright?
What is the how to guide for all this?
What's the short and sweet version?
So when it comes to this, how
do you assign hybrid orbitals
around your central atom?
So as I said before, if you wanna
watch the theory, rewind or go to my
full version for the short version.
All you're gonna do is you're gonna
determine your Lewis structure,
just like you've probably
been doing for a couple weeks.
Now, when it comes to all doing
that, you're gonna determine your
number of electron groups, right?
Or your steric number.
I, meaning you're counting how
many atoms and lone pairs there
are around your central atom.
Then you're gonna essentially assign a,
a hybrid or hybridized orbital to that.
It's gonna correspond to it.
So what I have down here is
I have like essentially the
final answer for everything.
So whenever you have a linear
geometry, Derrick, number
two, it's gonna be sp, right?
Two orbitals, S and P combined
together make sp right?
Whenever you have trigonal planar, right?
Three groups.
So you have S plus p,
plus P, a, k, a, SP two.
So three groups all
working together, right?
As we're kind of looking
at the structure, right?
All these are together.
We're gonna have S plus P plus P, and
it's gonna work together to make SP two.
Same thing with tetrahedral, right?
S plus P. Plus P plus P. 'cause
you have three P orbitals.
They're all gonna hybridize together
to assign, to rearrange those
four groups around tetrahedral.
You're gonna bio pyramidal.
Well, okay, you only have three p
orbitals, so what can you access next
that you're gonna access the D orbitals?
So this is what's gonna ex explain.
The expanded octet rule, meaning
whenever you violate the octet rule
by not following it right, it's like
you're like, okay, all of a sudden
some atoms can all of a sudden
have more than eight electrons.
Why?
This is why.
So it's the hybridization.
It allows to be able to
rearrange all your orbitals to
be able to bond to more things.
Same thing with octahedral, right?
You can go to SP 3D or SP 3D
two when you go to six groups.
And that's the limit, right?
For, for this general theory,
uh, generally goes up a six.
Um, anything at seven or eight or
more groups, that's usually when
you're doing coordination complexes.
That's not what this video's
gonna be focusing on.
That's all about how do we try to do this.
So, okay.
What does all this explain?
All right.
The first thing is it explains chemical
bonding through atomic orbital overlap.
I can't say that enough times.
I've already said it three times.
It's gonna utilize hybridization
to explain the vesper geometry.
So that's gonna be our whole idea,
right, is to get to the shapes.
Um, we're gonna be focusing on
sigma and py bonds, so we're
gonna be forming both those.
So sigmas are usually our single
bonds py bonds are gonna be used in
double and triple alongside sigma in.
The whole goal here is to minimize
energy and it's all based on
that atomic overlap, right?
So it's 'cause of all those orbitals
combining together, it's gonna have this.
You have to be able to understand
how to describe bond strength, right?
Complete proportion of overlap.
Stigma is always stronger in pie, and
you can look at Thermochemical data to
back that up if you study thermodynamics
or thermo chemistry at some point.
The other thing is that usually this
is always partnered with molecular
orbital theory, which will give
you a complete understanding of
molecular orbital swarming meaning.
This only covers so much, right?
This is a basic understanding.
It can go deeper and then
even deeper than that.
So it's kind of the idea, right?
Where we're gonna go, let's go
through some, a bunch of different
examples and try to see how this,
how, what else we can learn.
All right.
First thing is, is we're gonna be
kind of approaching this from the
theory standpoint, but also going
through how to do the examples.
So, all right, so if we had
the first one, beryllium.
Hydride, right?
So BEH two.
So the first step was that you had to
determine what the Lewis structure is.
So really quickly, you can
probably see, okay, beryllium
can bond to two different things.
Um, when it comes to looking at your
PR Act table, it's on the second,
second, uh, column, meaning you
can bond to two different things.
Okay.
If we were to look at how the electron
configuration is in our orbital diagrams,
you see they have two electrons in the
two s orbital, and hopefully now you're
kind of starting to see where errors are.
This looks like a problem.
You have two electrons already paired.
The first thing about the theory was
they had to be unpaired in order to bond.
So how the heck can that bond?
And it's not ionic, it's covalent
is what we're talking about.
Okay?
So that's the isolated atom.
So in order to do the bonding right,
to satisfy hydrogen, this thing
is willing to rearrange itself.
So, okay, what's the next step?
Next step was determine
the steric number, right?
So also, or also your geometry.
So we have Asteric number of two
a KAA linear geometry, right?
You can see it's 180 degrees.
This is linear.
So what does that mean?
Is SN is equal to two?
Is two atomic orbitals are
required to hybridize and
turn into two hybrid orbitals.
Okay, so we're gonna take one S orbital,
then we're gonna take one P orbital.
So S plus P is sp.
Now there's a problem, right?
You see that we started with
four lines, four orbitals
that are all over here, right?
We had 1, 2, 3, and four.
So if you start with four, you
have to have four when you're done.
So what happened to the other P orbitals?
They stay up at the top.
They didn't get touched, right?
So they just stay at their energy, but
they're just kind of empty at the moment.
So what were we gonna do is we're
gonna fill an electron in each
orbital because it's degenerate.
We fill across, just like you would
fill a P orbital or a d orbital or an
f orbital, you fill each one first.
Like I kind of say is every
electron wants its own room, um,
before it starts pairing back up.
So what does this allow us
to do is like, okay, wait.
We have an empty spot
now for each one of them.
So this is where the bonds can be made.
So what's kind of happening here?
So we combined an s and
a P orbital together.
So what are they gonna do?
Is they're gonna hybridize and
make essentially a new shape.
It doesn't, I know it doesn't
really, might look like, 'cause
my artwork's not the best, but it
kind of combines the two together.
You gotta keep in mind that S orbital,
even though I drew it really big,
it's way smaller than the p orbital.
So it's gonna kind of add them
together into their two versions.
So it's gonna make two sp orbitals.
That way it can bond both hydrogens.
So we'll add them together and that's
where we get the linear shape, right?
So you can see that 180.
So what we can do is we can kind of
overlay that with beryllium and it's
going to then bond to the two, the S
orbitals of each hydrogen on both sides.
Okay?
So put one hydrogen on one side, one
hydrogen on the other, so we can see,
okay, we have the SP orbital, and then
we have the S orbitals for hydrogen.
So the big thing is that depending
on your professor, right, you
probably have to describe the bonds.
So, okay, what do we got here, right?
So we got two of 'em, right?
We have one on the left
and one on the right.
So is it sigma or pie?
And that's the thing I think about, right?
It's a single bond.
So what are we gonna do?
Sig single is sigma.
Okay, so we have a sigma
bond and what's attached?
So we have the beryllium sp orbital.
His bonding.
And this is a dash, not a
minus or anything else, right?
So it's showing a bond and it's
combining with the hydrogen S orbital.
Right?
So they're combining together.
So that's what the bond is.
Now, when it comes to writing this,
I've seen it written both ways.
I've seen it written as hydrogen
with is an S. I've also seen in
some textbooks where they'll write
one s. I think it's kind of, it.
I don't really see it really
a huge kind of big deal,
depending one way or the other.
As long as you're aware it's the balance
level, which is one s here, right?
It's a little redundant, but you kind
of pay attention to how your, your
fa, your professor, or whoever's doing
your grading, how they did it in class.
SN equals the three.
All right, so star numbers three.
We have three orbitals are going in.
Three orbitals come out, right?
So SP plus P, it's gonna make
these three hybrid orbitals, right?
So to make SP two.
And when we overlap all of
them, it's gonna look like
the trigonal planer geometry.
Right?
So we're adding all
three of those together.
'cause they're overlapped, right?
So it's gonna make a triangle.
Okay.
Let's do it with BH three.
What's happening in terms of the energy?
Okay, so we have th boron, right?
So borons are central atom.
We got three balanced electrons.
And the first thing you're gonna notice
is that there's only one lonely electron.
So it can only make one bond.
That's not what's seen in physical data.
Alright, so what's gonna
happen to the borum?
How many hybrid orbitals do we need?
Well, we had asteric number
of three was what we had.
So if it's SN is equal to three, you're
gonna need three hybrid orbitals.
So put the three orbitals right in
between S and P, that'll be SP two.
The last P orbital is
gonna be up top right?
Four, one in four gotta come out.
You gotta write 'em all.
All right, so what are we
gonna do with those electrons?
We're gonna put one in each one
and now you can see that, hey,
you got a spot for each of those
bonds that are possible, right?
All half filled.
So that's our biggest thing.
So what does this help you show?
It actually helps show that the
deficient octet is actually okay.
It, all of 'em are at
the same energy level.
They're all filled up.
The one that's all the way up at the
top is like, eh, I'm already, I'm empty.
I'm up here.
I'm way too high to reach.
Anyway, that's kind of make, it
actually helps make some sense
outta some of these little, little
trends that are breaking every rule.
It's like chemistry.
The rules only work at
nine o'clock on a Tuesday.
When you're at s st at SSPT.
It's like, okay, well that's cool.
So how can we actually try to,
you know, use this to work?
So when we have the bonds right, you
can see that that s sp three orbitals.
So all three of them.
Are interacting with
each of the hydrogens.
So, okay.
How do we describe it?
We have three of these
orbitals that are interacting.
We have a sigma bond
that's interacting, right?
Single bond.
Um, being that if you were to
kind of draw it out, you'll see
that, hey, we have the boron.
It's all the hydrogens.
Um, and how would we describe it?
Well, okay, boron was SP two and I
don't know why we're SP three there.
It's known as SP two.
And it's going to be interacting
with the hydrogen S orbital, right?
So same orbital as before, right?
It's the atomic orbital because
it's only making one bond, so it
doesn't have to hybridize over here.
Only one that's making
a double or a triple.
Okay, cool.
So that would be trigonal
planer, and that's for BH three.
Let's go on to the next.
All right.
SN is equal to form.
This is when we're gonna add an S plus.
A p plus a P plus a P orbital.
So you have a little bit, you have
25% s and then 75% P character here.
Okay.
So we have the four atomic
orbitals are gonna come out.
You're gonna get four hybrid orbitals
that are gonna be here at the end.
And what they're all gonna end up doing
is you're gonna add all 'em together
to kind of make a tetrahedral shape.
So I tried my best there to make
that look like a right orbital shape.
That's usually not the
most important thing.
Most teachers don't, you don't
have to usually draw everything
like that, at least I hope.
But if you do, then okay.
Make sure you're aware of
how, how generally they look.
All right, so carbon, right?
So before we had four valence electrons.
So now we're gonna be able to
make the four bonds because
we had four atomic orbitals.
We have CF four, right?
So the structure is gonna
look something like this.
So you need four bonds.
Derrick number four.
So we need four hybrid orbitals.
Alright, 1, 2, 3, 4.
So we have SPPP.
We'll simplify that.
SP three.
Okay, so let's fill in our electrons.
We got one in each one and now
it makes a little bit more sense.
You have three openings for four bonds.
Before we only had two.
It's like how the hell did
carbon bond is So many things.
Does it make any sense?
So now it actually fills in
the entire picture, right?
Shouldn't accept anything at face value.
Alright, how do we actually write
in terms of describing the bonds?
So you gotta remember, what
was the last orbital for f. And
that's where, if you remember, it
was like two s, two two p five.
So it's gonna be the p orbital is what
this is gonna be bonding to, because
we're making just a single bond to that.
Okay?
So when you draw it, right, if you
have to draw the orbitals, you'd have
that tetrahedral geometry for carbon.
So that'd be SP three.
And then you're gonna try to
draw your best PR orbitals for
each of the floorings here.
So in order to describe the
bond, you're gonna have a sigma.
There's four of 'em.
So it'd be carbon is SP three and it's
gonna bond to a P orbital for flooring.
Right?
So actually not, not too bad, right?
The more you kind of practice.
So this is our tetrahedral shape.
Let's go into SN equal to five, SNS
equal to five and six is when it starts
explaining octet rule violations.
So when you get to the third row of
the PII table, the D orbital becomes.
Theoretically available based
on quantum numbers, right?
So if N is equal to three
L can be equal to two.
Now at the third row, the D
or or the D block isn't there
yet, but it exists, so, okay.
What can happen if we were to,
let's say, look at PCL five.
So I got the vesper structure
written there, right?
So you can see it has a
steric number of five.
So we got all these groups.
So static number five, that means
I need five hybrid orbitals.
I'm gonna have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
So how would I describe it, right?
I got S, P, PP, and ooh,
I'm out of p orbitals.
So this is where we
grab one from D, right?
So that's gonna be our new
one that we add into here.
So what're gonna do is we're
gonna simplify that SP 3D here.
I'll make that consistent, make that
green 'cause that's our new one.
Okay, so now is this kind of complete?
Well, all right, well, how many
de orbitals do I have left?
Right?
So there's still four that remain
up top 'cause we didn't touch them.
And what else do we have
to do with this picture?
So we have to fill in
our valance electrons.
So phosphorus has five.
So you can see originally it can only
make three bonds, but now we're gonna
be able to make a total of five bonds.
So we're gonna put one.
Arrow in each of these lines
and you can see, hey, we can
now make five single bonds.
That's incredible.
Right?
Okay.
So the next thing is right is what was
the last electron in chlorine, right?
So we can complete this picture.
So if you kind of remember, right,
it's three S, two, three P five.
So the last one is in the P
orbital or trying to explain this.
So if you were to kind of draw it, it's
gonna look something like this, right?
It's trigonal by pyramidal.
So, all right, what do we got here?
So in white, I have our
SP 3D orbitals, right?
So we got the five of them there.
So how are you gonna describe it, right?
You have five orbitals, all sigma,
so you're gonna describe that as or
as phosphorus, and it's gonna be SP
3D, and that's gonna be bonding to
our chlorine, which is, its P orbital
is what we're gonna be explaining.
As chlorine.
Right.
So that's our entire thing.
Yeah.
Five of 'em.
They're all kind of bonding together.
Let's do our last one for SN equal to six.
And whenever you see a noble gas
bonding, it's just like, it's
like, wait, when do they ever bond?
We were told, and especially when you
first started high school chem or whenever
you learn chem, that they can never bond.
But all of a sudden your teacher's
giving you these things and you're
like, this doesn't make sense.
We were always told, it's
like everything's alive.
So specifically when you write down
its its isolated atom structure.
You're gonna see that it
has no room for any bonds.
But what it can do is it can
rearrange itself and satisfy all
these fluorines that are around it.
So let's say if I had XT F
four, how would you do it?
So, okay.
First thing is we gotta count
how many groups we have, right?
So we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
So steric number is six.
So what are we gonna do is we're gonna
draw, draw six orbitals, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
And as a result, we also will have
three orbitals still remaining above.
So what is this new orbital, right?
We have S-P-P-P-D-D.
All right.
That's confusing.
Let's simplify.
Its SP 3D two, right?
So you had 2D orbitals, three
p orbitals will fill it in.
All right, so being that we're filling
this all in, right, it's all single bonds,
so everything's gonna be hybridized.
'cause lone pairs sit
in hybridized orbitals.
So we're gonna be filling
across, so we got six so far.
Then we're gonna double them
up Now, does this make sense?
Well, okay, let's take a look, right?
One of the things we had.
We had two double bonds.
Okay.
Or not double bonds,
sorry, two loan pairs.
So describes that.
Then we also have three openings
for, or, sorry, not three.
Oh my goodness.
Four openings for all of your
single bonds that are here, right?
So we have four openings for single bonds,
and we're describing our two loan pairs.
Phenomenal.
All right, let's kind of draw it.
So once again, we've done fluorine
a few times now, so we have our
orbitals, so let's describe them.
All right, so you have four single bonds.
They're all sigma.
And how would you describe that?
Well, it's xenon and that is,
it's SP 3D two orbital and it's
bonding to fluorine's e orbital.
Alright, so all that is connected.
We got four of 'em.
Now one thing question I usually get,
do you have to describe the lone pairs?
No.
Right.
They're just, they're a, this very
diffuse lone pair kind of sitting on top.
So I kind of drew them as like, you
know, these little, these little guys
that are kind of sitting here all happy.
Um, you know, kind of pushing
everything away from as the whole
idea with this electron geometry.
So this one would be octahedral
is the electron geometry.
The actual molecular
shape is square planer.
But this describes the
electron pair geometry.
Let's take a look at some
examples with doubles and triple
bonds and wrap this video up.
Alright, double bonds.
So whenever we do, a double has
to be a syn sigma, plus a pie
bond to make a double right.
It's four electrons.
So we need two orbitals to
house those four electrons.
So remembering sigma is hybridized.
Whenever we do pie, it's un
hybridized and pie has to be parallel.
Stigma is overlapped.
Okay, so now that really matters
when you're drawing them.
Um, meaning drawing the real shapes.
All right, so the first thing is
right, is how do we kind of do this?
So the first thing is you have
multiple central atoms here, right?
So we have a carbon, carbon,
they're both central, so, but
they're both gonna have the same.
Hybridization to them.
So let's say if we look at one of
them, we'll do the one on the left.
We're gonna count how many groups as
one, two, and then it has three, right?
That entire thing on
the right is one group.
Like I kind of joke with my students
is like, do atoms have eyeballs?
And they don't, right?
All they do is they
sense what's around it.
They're just trying to
space everything around it.
They want their personal space.
So there's three groups.
They're all gonna be kind
of far from each other.
Okay?
We have those three that are there
on that carbon, and it's gonna
be the same for the other one.
Okay.
What's Aster number three?
Well, okay, so it's S plus P plus
B. Those should be three of them.
So that's gonna be SP two
hybridization, and that's gonna
be the case for both carbons.
They're both SP two, um,
when you go through the work.
All right, so you're gonna write out
your original electron configuration.
That's SP two, then it means I
need three hybrid orbitals, and
that means you're gonna have one
that's gonna be up at the top.
Now, being that when we look at
one of these, all right, how many
single or sigmas do you have?
The form, right?
So there's one for each hydrogen, then
we have no, here, we'll label in red.
So we have one free each hydrogen
and out of the double bond.
Remember Sigma plus high.
So one of those is gonna be reserved
for the sigma portion of the CC bond.
The other one, this un hybridized one, is
gonna be where your pie bond is gonna go.
Okay, so we, this is where
it gets a little tricky.
So one electron is gonna be shoved all
the way up the top, reserved for doing
the double bond that is on the structure.
So let's take a look at what this thing
looks like in terms of trying to draw it.
Okay, so the first thing is
let's draw the hybrid orbitals.
So, okay, we had SP two, so it should
look like trigonal planar, right?
We want to kind of try to make it look
like a rough triangle, like so I know
I'm not the best artist, but that's okay.
So we'll do it for both, right?
They're both SP two and what you're,
what's connecting to those hybrid
orbitals as you have your hydrogens.
Okay?
So that's gonna be a little circle.
It's gonna be a little circle,
another circle, and then another one.
Okay, cool.
So we have most of the structure,
but how we describe the double bond.
Okay, so that p orbital that's left has
to be essentially a parallel orbital.
So usually what I like to do is I like
to draw two parallel lines, and I usually
favor the Y axis first before Z, but as
long as it's parallel, then you're okay.
Usually it's usually always goes Y, then
Z. But you can kind of, you, as long as
you do a parallel one, you'll be okay.
Okay, we have our green one here
is what's gonna be hybridized.
So here, lemme change that wording.
So green is un hybridized and the
way that you can draw this really
depends on who your instructor is.
I personally just like to connect it
with a green line, but the way that
this kind of really looks in terms
of drawing is that it kind of really
stretches the orbital between the two.
So it's extremely diffuse.
Um, I like to just connect them just
with a simple little line, but like I
kind of said, it really depends on how
your professor has drawn it in class.
So you got a pie bond, the sigma
and the pie are connecting together,
help show that interaction.
So you got a sigma, Sigma, sigma
for all the hydrogens, and then
you have that sigma and pie
in the middle for the double.
All right.
So how would you describe
the bonds though?
All right.
That's kinda the tricky part.
So, okay, we got four bonds that are
referencing the carbons to hydrogens.
So, okay, so you got carbon, it's SP two,
it's bonding to the hydrogen S, right?
So we've done that a few times now for
the double bond, you would describe
it as you have as Sigma CSP two,
going to our other carbon SP two.
And then it would have a pie bond.
That's CPCP.
'cause that's your un hybridized one.
Okay?
So both of these guys, this is
your double and the one on the
top is gonna be your hydrogens.
Okay?
So that's all the hydrogens.
So C to H, and then your
carbon to carbon, right?
Let's do one more, which is a triple bond.
Okay?
So whenever you have a triple bond,
this is when things get a little tricky.
Because you're not only doing aster
number, but you have to also make sure
that you're accounting for whatever atoms
are doing the double and the triple bond.
Because even if they're only
connected to one thing, because
they're doing a double or triple,
they have to be hybridized as well.
So what do I mean by that?
All right, so if I look at carbon,
right, it's attached to two things.
It's national nitrogen and a hydrogen.
So it has a SN of two.
So that's gonna be sp.
Now this nitrogen, on the other hand,
it's only connected to the carbon and
then also connected to a lone pair.
So even though this is not the proper
way to do geometries, you also can
assign it as being next to two groups.
Because when it comes to electron
pair geometry, it's all about how
many things is it connected to.
It's not about the
actual shape that's here.
So both of them are gonna
assume that s sp geometry.
Okay, so when we're kinda looking
here, right, so let's do carbon first.
So we had sp, so you're gonna
need two hybrid orbitals and
then two un hybridized orbitals.
So you'll fill in your electrons,
fill in two at the bottom, and
you're gonna need two up at the top.
Because remember, you need two pie bonds.
So, because we're making a triple, then
down here, this is gonna be a sigma.
One's gonna be for the h. And the
other one's gonna be sigma for the
nitrogen that's gonna be up here.
So now when it comes to nitrogen,
okay, so same thing, right?
So you got two s and then two P.
So you have five valent electrons.
So, okay, we need SP as well.
So same deal S and P, and
we'll have, we'll fill in our
electrons, so, okay, so same idea.
So we need to make sure we
fill in the geometry correctly.
So, all right, well
you're making a triple.
So we got our two pies, but
I have a missing one, right?
I had five uh, arrows on the left.
I have only four on the right.
What else do I need?
Well, this one has a loan
pair that's on it, right?
So we need to make sure that hey,
we account for that little loan
pair in our structure, and then we
also have room for a sigma bond.
And then also the two pies.
It gets a little, ugh, a little gross.
Alright, so 'cause of that nitrogen
having multiple, we have to hybridize.
So I saved a little time.
I drew the hybrid part and then
I drew the parallels as well.
So let's kinda show what I have.
So the purple is our SP hybrid.
So notice how it's linear, right?
It's going in a straight line
down this X axis here, right?
So you have the little lone
pair with the little red dots.
White is the Y parallel access,
green is the Z parallel access.
Right?
On the other side.
Right.
So that's gonna be the other thing.
Okay.
So our first lo, let's label,
so we have our sigma bond.
We have another sigma over here.
Then you have our first I double bond,
and then you have another one in the back.
Where you have a triple bond, right?
So you got a one that they're, there's
a cross between the two, right?
So both of those different
orbitals are interacting.
Ugh.
All right.
How do you describe it?
All right, let's do the, let's do the easy
one, which is the carbon, the hydrogen.
So, okay, carbon sp is interacting with
hydrogen s and you only have one of 'em.
Then we have our bonds
for our triple right.
So it's sigma.
Plus pi.
So we need to describe all of them.
Okay, so it's carbon SP to nitrogen,
sp, and then for one pie, it's
gonna be carbon, P to nitrogen,
P, and then you have another pie,
which is carbon, P to nitrogen, P.
Now, some instructors, they might
require you to label what's PY px,
pz, when you're labeling these two.
It depends on kind of you, right?
And how and how your
professor teaching it.
If they are labeling it, then obviously
wanna label that, um, just to kind
of, you know, be complete here, right?
So one of them would be like
y and then the other one would
be Z based on how I drew it.
Um, you know, usually a lot of
times Z is the interclear axis
when it comes to bonding, right?
So between the line down the middle.
So it just depends on your class, right?
If it's organic chem, usually
it's always a z. Alright?
Let's go through the normal
problems that you'll see with this.
Alright, let's take a look.
Alright.
The most common problem you're
gonna see is whenever you're just
given a molecule and you have to
label what the hybridization is.
So it's gonna like point to an atom and
you have to explain, say, Hey, what is it?
It's pretty easy.
It's memorizing that chart that I
showed you earlier, which was, you
know, linears, sp, then it'ss, SP twos,
SP three, SP 3D, SB 3D two, right?
So in that order, okay, so if
you were to do it right, so if we
look at a. So this is dopamine.
So how can we try to do it?
So the first one, right?
You're counting how many groups, right?
So we got 1, 2, 3, and then we
have the fourth one that's here.
Don't forget to count like
the whole molecule as a group.
Okay?
So three groups, or sorry, not
three groups, sorry, four groups.
So what is it gonna be Is S plus
P plus P plus P. That's SP three.
All right.
If we go to B. All right.
How many groups do you got?
Right?
So we're gonna be counting here.
We got the double bond leads to one.
The single bond leads to the other.
Hydrogen leads to the other.
So this is two, so the, or sorry, not two.
So it's three total.
So how would we do that?
That would be SP two, right?
So counting each of
those different pieces.
All right.
C. All right.
So if I look at the oxygen on the
other hand, all right, we got the
hydrogen, the one that's attached
to the carbon, and then you have
the lone pairs that are up here.
So four groups.
So once again, it's gonna be SP three.
Same thing with D. How do you do that one?
Well, same idea.
You got one group, two groups,
three groups, four groups.
But once again, it's SP three.
That's kind of when it gets a lot
easier is that when you look at organic
chemicals, mainly it goes with s SP three.
Very rarely do you see a chemical
that goes beyond that because
that's usually never organic.
Um, and this is usually the most
common area that you'll have
to know for organic chemistry.
It's labeling because it helps you
with NMR spectroscopy, IR spectroscopy,
how to be able to understand
geometries for predicting what you're
making and that's the most common.
The other thing that you could have too
is maybe if like someone points to a bond
and they're like, Hey, describe that bond.
So, okay, if I were to do that one
right Sigma, and you say carbon and
one of 'em was SP two, and then the
other one would also be SP two, right?
Because it's, um.
Three groups around each of them.
So you, that could be another one where
you could try to describe it without
even drawing it, um, just by labeling.
Okay.
All right, so that is, that,
that's everything I had.
I know it was a longer one, but hopefully
this helps you right to be able to
go over all the details when it comes
to hybridization, how to do this.
If you have questions, please post them.
Please message me, reach out, and
thank you so much for watching.
I hope that this video
helped you a little bit.
And I, I look forward to
seeing you in the future.
All right, y'all have a wonderful,
wonderful day, and I'll see y'all later.
Bye now.